<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ********************************************************************
     $Id: front.xml,v 1.2 2002/12/20 22:29:48 nilgun Exp $
******************************************************************** -->
<chapter id="pylib-front">
  <title>Front Matter</title>
<para>Copyright © 2001-2006 Python Software Foundation. All rights
reserved.</para>
<para>Copyright © 2000 BeOpen.com. All rights reserved.</para>
<para>Copyright © 1995-2000 Corporation for National Research
Initiatives. All rights reserved.</para>
<para>Copyright © 1991-1995 Stichting Mathematisch Centrum. All rights
reserved.</para>
<para>See the end of this document for complete license and
permissions information.</para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect3">Abstract:</bridgehead>
<para>Python is an extensible, interpreted, object-oriented
programming language. It supports a wide range of applications,
from simple text processing scripts to interactive Web
browsers.</para>
<para>While the <ulink url="http://www.python.org/doc/current/ref/ref.html">Python Reference Manual</ulink>
describes the exact syntax and semantics of the language, it does
not describe the standard library that is distributed with the
language, and which greatly enhances its immediate usability. This
library contains built-in modules (written in C) that provide
access to system functionality such as file I/O that would
otherwise be inaccessible to Python programmers, as well as modules
written in Python that provide standardized solutions for many
problems that occur in everyday programming. Some of these modules
are explicitly designed to encourage and enhance the portability of
Python programs.</para>
<para>This library reference manual documents Python's standard
library, as well as many optional library modules (which may or may
not be available, depending on whether the underlying platform
supports them and on the configuration choices made at compile
time). It also documents the standard types of the language and its
built-in functions and exceptions, many of which are not or
incompletely documented in the Reference Manual.</para>
<para>This manual assumes basic knowledge about the Python language.
For an informal introduction to Python, see the<ulink url="http://www.python.org/doc/current/tut/tut.html">Python Tutorial</ulink>; the<ulink url="http://www.python.org/doc/current/ref/ref.html">Python Reference Manual</ulink> remains
the highest authority on syntactic and semantic questions. Finally,
the manual entitled <ulink url="http://www.python.org/doc/current/ext/ext.html">Extending
and Embedding the Python Interpreter</ulink> describes how to add
new extensions to Python and how to embed it in other
applications.</para>
</chapter>