<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ********************************************************************
        libc/glibc.xml,v2.36, GFDL-1.3,LGPL-2.1, NBB, 2023
     ******************************************************************** -->
<book xml:id="glibc" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
      xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="tr">
<?dbhtml dir="../glibc"?>
 <title>GNU C Kütüphanesi Başvuru Kılavuzu</title>
 <info>
  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Sandra Loosemore</firstname>
    </personname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Richard M. Stallman</firstname>
    </personname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Roland McGrath</firstname>
    </personname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Andrew Oram</firstname>
    </personname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <personname>
     <firstname>Ulrich Drepper</firstname>
    </personname>
   </author>
   <author role="translator">
    <personname>
     <firstname>Nilgün Belma Bugüner</firstname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <address>
      <link xl:href="https://github.com/nilgun"/>
     </address>
    </affiliation>
   </author>
   <author role="translator">
    <personname>
     <firstname>Yaşar Dereli</firstname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
     <address>
      <link xl:href="https://www.deu.edu.tr">Dokuz Eylül Üniversitesi</link>
     </address>
    </affiliation>
   </author>
  </authorgroup>
  <date>18 Ekim 2004</date>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    Bu kitap GNU C kütüphanesini belgelendirir (güncelleme henüz bitmedi).
   </para>
   <para>
    Çeviri, ... 2023'te kılavuzun libc-2.36 paketiyle dağıtılan sürümünden ... (güncelleme henüz bitmedi)
   </para>
  </abstract>
  <legalnotice>
   <title>Özgün Belge için Yasal Uyarı</title>
   <para>
    Copyright © 1993-2022 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
   </para>
   <para>
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being “Free Software Needs Free Documentation” and “GNU Lesser General Public License”, the Front-Cover texts being “A GNU Manual”, and with the Back-Cover Texts as in (a) below.  A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
   </para>
   <para>
    (a) The FSF's Back-Cover Text is: “You are free to copy and modify this GNU Manual. Buying copies from GNU Press supports the FSF in developing GNU and promoting software freedom.”
   </para>
  </legalnotice>
  <legalnotice>
   <title>Türkçe Çeviri için Yasal Uyarı</title>
   <para>
    Bu kitabın, <emphasis>GNU C Kütüphanesi Başvuru Kılavuzu</emphasis>, Türkçe çevirisinin <emphasis role="bold">telif hakkı © 2003-2022 <emphasis>Nilgün Belma Bugüner</emphasis> ve <emphasis>Yaşar Dereli</emphasis></emphasis>'ye aittir.
   </para>
   <para>
    Bu belgeyi; GNU Özgür Belgelendirme Lisansının 1.3 veya daha sonraki bir sürümüne sadık kalmak koşulu ile kopyalayabilir, dağıtabilir veya düzenleyebilirsiniz. GNU Özgür Belgelendirme Lisansı, Free Software Foundation tarafından yayınlanmaktadır. Değiştirilemez bölüm olarak "<xref linkend="glibc-Free-Manuals-en"/>" ve "<xref linkend="glibc-Copying"/>"  ile aşağıdaki Ön kapak yazısı (a) ve Arka kapak yazısı (b) bulunmalıdır. Bu Lisansın bir kopyasını <xref linkend="glibc-Documentation-License"/>" başlıklı bölümde bulabilirsiniz.
   </para>
   <para>
    Kitap içeriğindeki bilgileri uygulama sorumluluğu uygulayana aittir.
   </para>
   <para>
    BU KİTAP "ÜCRETSİZ" OLARAK RUHSATLANDIĞI İÇİN, İÇERDİĞİ BİLGİLER İÇİN İLGİLİ KANUNLARIN İZİN VERDİĞİ ÖLÇÜDE HERHANGİ BİR GARANTİ VERİLMEMEKTEDİR. AKSİ YAZILI OLARAK BELİRTİLMEDİĞİ MÜDDETÇE TELİF HAKKI SAHİPLERİ VE/VEYA BAŞKA ŞAHISLAR KİTABI "OLDUĞU GİBİ", AŞİKAR VEYA ZIMNEN, SATILABİLİRLİĞİ VEYA HERHANGİ BİR AMACA UYGUNLUĞU DA DAHİL OLMAK ÜZERE HİÇBİR GARANTİ VERMEKSİZİN DAĞITMAKTADIRLAR. BİLGİNİN KALİTESİ İLE İLGİLİ TÜM SORUNLAR SİZE AİTTİR. HERHANGİ BİR HATALI BİLGİDEN DOLAYI DOĞABİLECEK OLAN BÜTÜN SERVİS, TAMİR VEYA DÜZELTME MASRAFLARI SİZE AİTTİR.
   </para>
   <para>
    İLGİLİ KANUNUN İCBAR ETTİĞİ DURUMLAR VEYA YAZILI ANLAŞMA HARİCİNDE HERHANGİ BİR ŞEKİLDE TELİF HAKKI SAHİBİ VEYA YUKARIDA İZİN VERİLDİĞİ ŞEKİLDE KİTABI DEĞİŞTİREN VEYA YENİDEN DAĞITAN HERHANGİ BİR KİŞİ, BİLGİNİN KULLANIMI VEYA KULLANILAMAMASI (VEYA VERİ KAYBI OLUŞMASI, VERİNİN YANLIŞ HALE GELMESİ, SİZİN VEYA ÜÇÜNCÜ ŞAHISLARIN ZARARA UĞRAMASI VEYA BİLGİLERİN BAŞKA BİLGİLERLE UYUMSUZ OLMASI) YÜZÜNDEN OLUŞAN GENEL, ÖZEL, DOĞRUDAN YA DA DOLAYLI HERHANGİ BİR ZARARDAN, BÖYLE BİR TAZMİNAT TALEBİ TELİF HAKKI SAHİBİ VEYA İLGİLİ KİŞİYE BİLDİRİLMİŞ OLSA DAHİ, SORUMLU DEĞİLDİR.
   </para>
  </legalnotice>
 </info>
 <dedication><title>Teşekkür</title>
  <simplelist>
   <member>
    Kılavuzun çevirisi sırasında zorlandığım ya da çelişkiye düştüğüm yerlerde, yardımlarını esirgemeyen, kardeşim Yücel Haluk Bugüner'e,
   </member>
   <member>
    yerelleştirme ile ilgili çalışmalarda yoldaşım olan <link xl:href="http://www.arayan.com/">Deniz Akkuş</link>'a,
   </member>
   <member>
    bir yıldan uzun bir süre boyunca bıkmadan usanmadan kimi zaman her gün bol miktarda yazım hatası bildiren Türksat Mühendisi Ömer GÜLMEN'e
   </member>
  </simplelist>
  <simpara>
   teşekkür ederim.
  </simpara>
  <simpara>
   Nilgün Belma Bugüner -- 2004-2023
  </simpara>
 </dedication>
 <preface xml:id="glibc-hakkinda"><title>Çeviri Hakkında</title>
  <para>
   GNU C Kütüphanesi Kılavuzu gibi kapsamlı bir C işlevleri kılavuzu şimdiye dek Türkçe'ye çevrilmemişti (bildiğim kadarıyla). Her ne kadar C dili ile geliştirilen bir yazılım teamülen tamamen İngilizce sözcüklerle yazılıyorsa da, ülkemizde hiç İngilizce bilmeyenlerin de C ile yazılım geliştirebildiklerini biliyoruz.
  </para>
  <para>
   Belgeler.org ya da az bilinen ismimizle "Linux Belgelendirme Çalışma Grubu" olarak özgür kaynak kodlu yazılımların özgür belgelerini Türkçeye çevirme görevini *gönüllü* olarak üstlendiğimizden, ilk olarak çok gereksinim duyulan bu kılavuzu çevirmeye karar verdik ve kılavuzun İngilizce tam metnini tefrika bölümüne yerleştirip çeviriye gönüllü katılım daveti yaptık (17 Ağustos 2003).
  </para>
  <para>
   İlk bölümleri ben çevirdim, bir süre sonra Yaşar Dereli bazı bölümlerin çevirisini üstlendi ve <xref linkend="glibc-Cryptographic-Functions"/>, <xref linkend="glibc-Sockets"/>, <xref linkend="glibc-Processes"/> ve <xref linkend="glibc-Pipes-and-FIFOs"/> oylumlarını çevirdi. Evlendikten sonra sanırım pek fırsat bulamadı ve bunu sürdüremedi. Başka üstleniciler de oldu ama onlar bu kararlarının gereğini yerine getirmediler. Sonuçta, Yaşar Dereli'nin çevirdiği oylumlar hariç kılavuzun kalanı benim tarafımdan çevrildi.
  </para>
  <para>
   Böyle bir kılavuzun ilk defa çevrilmeye çalışılmasının bazı zorlukları vardı. Bazı terimlerin türkçe karşılıkları hiç yoktu.
  </para>
  <para>
   Kılavuzda C diline özgü işlev, makro, veri türü, HTML dosya isimleri gibi sözcükler dışında İngilizce terim yoktur. Dosya isimlerine dokunulmamasının sebebi özgün metinle çeviri arasında kolay bağ kurulabilmesini sağlamaktır.
  </para>
  <para>
   Kılavuzda kullanılan dile özel bir dikkat gösterilmiştir. Kavramsal karmaşaya yol açmamak için terimler özenle seçilmiştir. Kimi yerde bir terim size şaşırtıcı gelebilir. Bunun sebebi, orada kullanılması gerektiğini düşündüğünüz terimin içerdiği kavramla daha iyi örtüşen bir yerde o terimin kullanılmış olması, orada ise yine o terim kullanıldığında bir kavram kargaşasına yol açacak olmasıdır. Bu bakımdan kılavuz içinde karşılaştığınız yeni terimleri bulunduğu bağlam içinde değerlendirmelisiniz. Örneğin, "thread" için şimdiye kadar çeşitli kaynaklarda "kanal, iplik" gibi karşılığı kullanılmış (bence hiç de kavramla örtüşmüyor). Kılavuz içinde ise dosya akımları ile dosya tanıtıcılarından birlikte bahsedilirken kullanılan bir terim bu "kanal" hazretleri. Dolayısıyla kılavuz kapsamında "thread" için "evre" karşılığı kullanılmıştır. Burada bahsedemeyeceğim daha çook yeni terim var ama metni okurken, metin anlamlarınıda içerdiğinden onları kolay kolay farketmeyecek ve doğal olarak sizler de onları kullanmaya başlayacaksınız.
  </para>
  <para>
   Ayrıca, özellikle bu kılavuz için, işlevlerin HTML sayfalar üzerindeki şimdiki görüntüsünü elde etmek için ve kılavuzun sonundaki dizinleri elde etmek için Docbook-xsl kodlarında değişiklik yapılmıştır. Eğer kılavuzun PDF çıktısını almak için XML taslaklarını standart DocBook-xsl kodları ile derlerseniz bu çıktıyı elde edemezsiniz (hatta hiç derleyemezsiniz). Bunun yerine XML taslakları aldığınız yerde bulunan belgeler xsl kodunun  (<filename>source/docbook/xsl/belgeler</filename>) yanında belgeler.dtd (<filename>source/docbook/dtd/belgeler.dtd</filename>) kodunu alıp kullanmalısınız. (Bu durum belgeler.org.tr'deki bütün belgelerin XML taslakları için geçerlidir. belgeler.org.tr herşeyiyle özel ve bu özellikleriyle bir bütünlük içindedir.)
  </para>
  <para>
   Kılavuzun, C diliyle yazılım geliştirenler ve C diliyle yazılım geliştirmeseler bile tüm Linux kullananlar tarafından en azından bir kere okunmasını öneririm. Kafalarındaki pek çok sorunun yanıtını bu kılavuzun içinde bulacaklarına ve bu kılavuzu başucu kılavuzu haline getireceklerine eminim.
  </para>
  <para>
   Eğer kılavuzunun metni içinde çevrilmemiş, çevrildiği halde orada kalmış metinlere rastlarsanız ya da bir imla hatası bulursanız lütfen <link xl:href="https://github.com/TLBP">TLBP</link> üzerinden bildirin.
  </para>
  <para>Nilgün Belma Bugüner -- 2004-2023.</para>
 </preface>

&libc-ch01.xml;
&libc-ch02.xml;
&libc-ch03.xml;
&libc-ch04.xml;
&libc-ch05.xml;
&libc-ch06.xml;
&libc-ch07.xml;
&libc-ch08.xml;
&libc-ch09.xml;
&libc-ch10.xml;
&libc-ch11.xml;
&libc-ch12.xml;
&libc-ch13.xml;
&libc-ch14.xml;
&libc-ch15.xml;
&libc-ch16.xml;
&libc-ch17.xml;
&libc-ch18.xml;
&libc-ch19.xml;
&libc-ch20.xml;
&libc-ch21.xml;
&libc-ch22.xml;
&libc-ch23.xml;
&libc-ch24.xml;
&libc-ch25.xml;
&libc-ch26.xml;
&libc-ch27.xml;
&libc-ch28.xml;
&libc-ch29.xml;
&libc-ch30.xml;
&libc-ch31.xml;
&libc-ch32.xml;
&libc-ch33.xml;
&libc-ch34.xml;
&libc-ch35.xml;
&libc-ch36.xml;
&libc-ch37.xml;
&libc-ch38.xml;
&libc-appa.xml;
&libc-appb.xml;
&libc-appc.xml;
&libc-appd.xml;
&libc-appe.xml;
&libc-appf.xml;

 <appendix xml:id="glibc-Free-Manuals-tr">
  <title>Özgür Yazılımın Özgür Belgelere İhtiyacı Var</title>
  <para>
   <indexterm role="cp"><primary>özgür belgeleme</primary></indexterm>
   Bugün özgür yazılım topluluğundaki en büyük eksiklik yazılımda değil; özgür yazılıma dahil edebileceğimiz iyi özgür belgelerin olmamasıdır. En önemli programlarımızın çoğu, özgür başvuru kılavuzları ve özgür giriş metinleriyle birlikte gelmez. Belgelendirme, herhangi bir yazılım paketinin önemli bir parçasıdır; Önemli bir özgür yazılım paketi, özgür bir kılavuz ve özgür bir öğretici ile gelmediğinde, bu büyük bir boşluktur. Bugün bunun gibi birçok açığımız var.
  </para>
  <para>
   Örneğin Perl'i ele alalım. İnsanların normalde kullandığı öğretici kılavuzlar özgür değildir. Bu nasıl oldu? Çünkü bu kılavuzların yazarları, onları özgür yazılım dünyasının dışında bırakan kısıtlayıcı koşullarla -kopyalama yok, değişiklik yok, kaynak dosyalar yok- yayınladı.
  </para>
  <para>
   Bu tür şeyler ilk kez olmuyordu ve sonuncusu da olmaktan çok uzaktı. Çoğu zaman, bir GNU kullanıcısının yazdığı bir el kitabını, topluluğa amaçlanan katkısını hevesle anlattığını, ancak onu özgür olmayan hale getirmek için bir yayın sözleşmesi imzalayarak her şeyi mahvettiğini öğrendiğini duyduk.
  </para>
  <para>
   Özgür yazılım gibi özgür belgeleme de bir fiyat meselesi değil, bir özgürlük meselesidir. Özgür olmayan el kitabıyla ilgili sorun, yayıncıların basılı kopyalar için bir fiyat talep etmesi değil - bu kendi içinde sorun değil. (Özgür Yazılım Vakfı, kılavuzların basılı kopyalarını da satmaktadır.) Sorun, kılavuzun kullanımına ilişkin kısıtlamalardır. Özgür kılavuzlar kaynak kodu biçiminde mevcuttur ve size kopyalama ve değiştirme izni verir. Özgür olmayan kılavuzlar buna izin vermez.
  </para>
  <para>
   Özgür bir el kitabı için özgürlük kriterleri, özgür yazılımla kabaca aynıdır. Yeniden dağıtıma (normal ticari yeniden dağıtım türleri dahil) izin verilmelidir, böylece kılavuz hem çevrimiçi hem de kağıt üzerinde yazılımın her kopyasına eşlik edebilir.
  </para>
  <para>
   Teknik içeriğin değiştirilmesine izin verilmesi de çok önemlidir. İnsanlar yazılımı değiştirdiklerinde, özellikler ekleyerek veya değiştirdiklerinde, dikkatli olurlarsa kılavuzu da değiştirirler - böylece değiştirilen yazılım için doğru ve net belgeler sağlayabilirler. Size yazılımın değiştirilmiş bir sürümünü belgelemek için yeni bir kılavuz yazmaktan başka seçenek bırakmayan bir kılavuz, topluluğumuz için gerçekten kullanılabilir değildir.
  </para>
  <para>
   Değişikliğin ele alınma şekline ilişkin bazı sınırlar kabul edilebilir. Örneğin, yazarın özgün telif hakkı bildirimini, dağıtım şartlarını veya yazar listesini koruma gereklilikleri kabul edilebilir.. Ayrıca, değiştirilen sürümlerin değiştirildiğine dair bildirim içermesini istemek de sorun değil. Teknik olmayan konuları ele aldıkları sürece (bunun gibi) silinemeyecek veya değiştirilemeyecek tüm bölümler bile kabul edilebilir. Bu tür kısıtlamalar, topluluğun kılavuzu normal şekilde kullanmasını engellemediği için kabul edilebilir.
  </para>
  <para>
   Bununla birlikte, kılavuzun tüm teknik içeriğini değiştirmek ve ardından sonucu tüm olağan ortamlarda, tüm olağan kanallar aracılığıyla dağıtmak mümkün olmalıdır . Aksi takdirde, kısıtlamalar kılavuzun kullanımını engeller ve kılavuz değiştirilemediği için başka bir kılavuz yazmaya mecbur bırakır.
  </para>
  <para>
   Lütfen bu konu hakkında duyuru yapınız. Topluluğumuz, el kitaplarını özel yayıncılığa kaptırmaya devam ediyor. Özgür yazılımın özgür başvuru kılavuzlarına ve özgür öğreticilere ihtiyacı olduğunu söylersek, belki de belge yazarak katkıda bulunmak isteyen bir sonraki kişi, çok geç olmadan, özgür yazılım topluluğuna yalnızca özgür kılavuzların katkıda bulunduğunu fark edecektir.
  </para>
  <para>
   Belge yazıyorsanız, lütfen onu GNU Özgür Belgeleme Lisansı veya başka bir özgür belgeleme lisansı altında yayınlamakta ısrar edin. Bu kararın sizin onayınızı gerektirdiğini unutmayın; kararı yayıncıya bırakmak zorunda değilsiniz. Bazı ticari yayıncılar, ısrar etmeniz halinde ücretsiz bir lisans kullanacaktır, ama bu seçeneği önermeyeceklerdir; konuyu gündeme getirmek ve istediğinizin bu olduğunu kesin bir şekilde söylemek size kalmış. Bir yayıncı reddederse, lütfen diğer yayıncıları deneyin. Önerilen lisansın ücretsiz olup olmadığından emin değilseniz,  licensing (at) gnu.org adresine yazın .
  </para>
  <para>
   Ticari yayıncıları daha fazla özgür, copyleft kılavuzları ve eğitimleri satın alarak ve özellikle de yazıları veya büyük iyileştirmeleri için ödeme yapan yayıncılardan kopyalar satın alarak satmaya teşvik edebilirsiniz. Bu arada, özgür olmayan belgeler satın almaktan kesinlikle kaçınmaya çalışın. Bir kılavuzu satın almadan önce dağıtım şartlarını kontrol edin ve işinizi arayan herkesin özgürlüğünüze saygı duyması gerektiğinde ısrar edin. Kitabın geçmişini kontrol edin ve üzerinde çalışmaları için yazarlara ödeme yapan yayıncıları ödüllendirmeyi deneyin.
  </para>
  <para>
   Özgür Yazılım Vakfı, diğer yayıncılar tarafından yayınlanan özgür belgelerin listesini <link xl:href="http://www.fsf.org/doc/other-free-books.html"/> adresinde bulundurmaktadır.
  </para>
 </appendix>

 <appendix xml:id="glibc-Free-Manuals-en">
  <title>Free Software Needs Free Documentation</title>
  <titleabbrev>DEĞİŞTİRİLEMEZ BÖLÜM. (ingilizce)</titleabbrev>
  <para>
The biggest deficiency in the free software community today is not in
the software--it is the lack of good free documentation that we can
include with the free software.  Many of our most important
programs do not come with free reference manuals and free introductory
texts.  Documentation is an essential part of any software package;
when an important free software package does not come with a free
manual and a free tutorial, that is a major gap.  We have many such
gaps today.
  </para>
  <para>
Consider Perl, for instance.  The tutorial manuals that people
normally use are non-free.  How did this come about?  Because the
authors of those manuals published them with restrictive terms--no
copying, no modification, source files not available--which exclude
them from the free software world.
  </para>
  <para>
That wasn't the first time this sort of thing happened, and it was far
from the last.  Many times we have heard a GNU user eagerly describe a
manual that he is writing, his intended contribution to the community,
only to learn that he had ruined everything by signing a publication
contract to make it non-free.
  </para>
  <para>
Free documentation, like free software, is a matter of freedom, not
price.  The problem with the non-free manual is not that publishers
charge a price for printed copies--that in itself is fine.  (The Free
Software Foundation sells printed copies of manuals, too.)  The
problem is the restrictions on the use of the manual.  Free manuals
are available in source code form, and give you permission to copy and
modify.  Non-free manuals do not allow this.
  </para>
  <para>
The criteria of freedom for a free manual are roughly the same as for
free software.  Redistribution (including the normal kinds of
commercial redistribution) must be permitted, so that the manual can
accompany every copy of the program, both on-line and on paper.
  </para>
  <para>
Permission for modification of the technical content is crucial too.
When people modify the software, adding or changing features, if they
are conscientious they will change the manual too--so they can
provide accurate and clear documentation for the modified program.  A
manual that leaves you no choice but to write a new manual to document
a changed version of the program is not really available to our
community.
  </para>
  <para>
Some kinds of limits on the way modification is handled are
acceptable.  For example, requirements to preserve the original
author's copyright notice, the distribution terms, or the list of
authors, are ok.  It is also no problem to require modified versions
to include notice that they were modified.  Even entire sections that
may not be deleted or changed are acceptable, as long as they deal
with nontechnical topics (like this one).  These kinds of restrictions
are acceptable because they don't obstruct the community's normal use
of the manual.
  </para>
  <para>
However, it must be possible to modify all the <emphasis>technical</emphasis>
content of the manual, and then distribute the result in all the usual
media, through all the usual channels.  Otherwise, the restrictions
obstruct the use of the manual, it is not free, and we need another
manual to replace it.
  </para>
  <para>
Please spread the word about this issue.  Our community continues to
lose manuals to proprietary publishing.  If we spread the word that
free software needs free reference manuals and free tutorials, perhaps
the next person who wants to contribute by writing documentation will
realize, before it is too late, that only free manuals contribute to
the free software community.
  </para>
  <para>
If you are writing documentation, please insist on publishing it under
the GNU Free Documentation License or another free documentation
license.  Remember that this decision requires your approval--you
don't have to let the publisher decide.  Some commercial publishers
will use a free license if you insist, but they will not propose the
option; it is up to you to raise the issue and say firmly that this is
what you want.  If the publisher you are dealing with refuses, please
try other publishers.  If you're not sure whether a proposed license
is free, write to <link xl:href="mailto:licensing@@gnu.org"></link>.
  </para>
  <para>
You can encourage commercial publishers to sell more free, copylefted
manuals and tutorials by buying them, and particularly by buying
copies from the publishers that paid for their writing or for major
improvements.  Meanwhile, try to avoid buying non-free documentation
at all.  Check the distribution terms of a manual before you buy it,
and insist that whoever seeks your business must respect your freedom.
Check the history of the book, and try reward the publishers that have
paid or pay the authors to work on it.
  </para>
  <para>
The Free Software Foundation maintains a list of free documentation
published by other publishers, at <link xl:href="http://www.fsf.org/doc/other-free-books.html"/>.
  </para>
 </appendix>

 <appendix xml:id="glibc-Copying">
  <title>GNU Lesser General Public License</title>
   <titleabbrev>DEĞİŞTİRİLEMEZ BÖLÜM. (ingilizce)</titleabbrev>
   <para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>LGPL, Lesser General Public License</primary></indexterm>
Version 2.1, February 1999
   </para>
   <screen>Copyright © 1991, 1999 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
59 Temple Place -- Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA

Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.

[This is the first released version of the Lesser GPL.  It also counts
as the successor of the GNU Library Public License, version 2, hence the
version number 2.1.]
</screen>
   <bridgehead renderas="sect2">Preamble</bridgehead>
   <para>
The licenses for most software are designed to take away your
freedom to share and change it.  By contrast, the GNU General Public
Licenses are intended to guarantee your freedom to share and change
free software--to make sure the software is free for all its users.
   </para>
   <para>
This license, the Lesser General Public License, applies to some
specially designated software--typically libraries--of the Free
Software Foundation and other authors who decide to use it.  You can use
it too, but we suggest you first think carefully about whether this
license or the ordinary General Public License is the better strategy to
use in any particular case, based on the explanations below.
   </para>
   <para>
When we speak of free software, we are referring to freedom of use,
not price.  Our General Public Licenses are designed to make sure that
you have the freedom to distribute copies of free software (and charge
for this service if you wish); that you receive source code or can get
it if you want it; that you can change the software and use pieces of it
in new free programs; and that you are informed that you can do these
things.
   </para>
   <para>
To protect your rights, we need to make restrictions that forbid
distributors to deny you these rights or to ask you to surrender these
rights.  These restrictions translate to certain responsibilities for
you if you distribute copies of the library or if you modify it.
   </para>
   <para>
For example, if you distribute copies of the library, whether gratis
or for a fee, you must give the recipients all the rights that we gave
you.  You must make sure that they, too, receive or can get the source
code.  If you link other code with the library, you must provide
complete object files to the recipients, so that they can relink them
with the library after making changes to the library and recompiling
it.  And you must show them these terms so they know their rights.
   </para>
   <para>
We protect your rights with a two-step method: (1) we copyright the
library, and (2) we offer you this license, which gives you legal
permission to copy, distribute and/or modify the library.
   </para>
   <para>
To protect each distributor, we want to make it very clear that
there is no warranty for the free library.  Also, if the library is
modified by someone else and passed on, the recipients should know
that what they have is not the original version, so that the original
author's reputation will not be affected by problems that might be
introduced by others.
   </para>
   <para>
Finally, software patents pose a constant threat to the existence of
any free program.  We wish to make sure that a company cannot
effectively restrict the users of a free program by obtaining a
restrictive license from a patent holder.  Therefore, we insist that
any patent license obtained for a version of the library must be
consistent with the full freedom of use specified in this license.
   </para>
   <para>
Most GNU software, including some libraries, is covered by the
ordinary GNU General Public License.  This license, the GNU Lesser
General Public License, applies to certain designated libraries, and
is quite different from the ordinary General Public License.  We use
this license for certain libraries in order to permit linking those
libraries into non-free programs.
   </para>
   <para>
When a program is linked with a library, whether statically or using
a shared library, the combination of the two is legally speaking a
combined work, a derivative of the original library.  The ordinary
General Public License therefore permits such linking only if the
entire combination fits its criteria of freedom.  The Lesser General
Public License permits more lax criteria for linking other code with
the library.
   </para>
   <para>
We call this license the <firstterm>Lesser</firstterm> General Public License because it
does <emphasis>Less</emphasis> to protect the user's freedom than the ordinary General
Public License.  It also provides other free software developers Less
of an advantage over competing non-free programs.  These disadvantages
are the reason we use the ordinary General Public License for many
libraries.  However, the Lesser license provides advantages in certain
special circumstances.
   </para>
   <para>
For example, on rare occasions, there may be a special need to
encourage the widest possible use of a certain library, so that it becomes
a de-facto standard.  To achieve this, non-free programs must be
allowed to use the library.  A more frequent case is that a free
library does the same job as widely used non-free libraries.  In this
case, there is little to gain by limiting the free library to free
software only, so we use the Lesser General Public License.
   </para>
   <para>
In other cases, permission to use a particular library in non-free
programs enables a greater number of people to use a large body of
free software.  For example, permission to use the GNU C Library in
non-free programs enables many more people to use the whole GNU
operating system, as well as its variant, the GNU/Linux operating
system.
   </para>
   <para>
Although the Lesser General Public License is Less protective of the
users' freedom, it does ensure that the user of a program that is
linked with the Library has the freedom and the wherewithal to run
that program using a modified version of the Library.
   </para>
   <para>
The precise terms and conditions for copying, distribution and
modification follow.  Pay close attention to the difference between a
"work based on the library" and a "work that uses the library".  The
former contains code derived from the library, whereas the latter must
be combined with the library in order to run.
   </para>
   <orderedlist numeration="arabic" inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
    <listitem>
     <para>
This License Agreement applies to any software library or other program
which contains a notice placed by the copyright holder or other
authorized party saying it may be distributed under the terms of this
Lesser General Public License (also called "this License").  Each
licensee is addressed as "you".
     </para>
     <para>
A "library" means a collection of software functions and/or data
prepared so as to be conveniently linked with application programs
(which use some of those functions and data) to form executables.
     </para>
     <para>
The "Library", below, refers to any such software library or work
which has been distributed under these terms.  A "work based on the
Library" means either the Library or any derivative work under
copyright law: that is to say, a work containing the Library or a
portion of it, either verbatim or with modifications and/or translated
straightforwardly into another language.  (Hereinafter, translation is
included without limitation in the term "modification".)
     </para>
     <para>
"Source code" for a work means the preferred form of the work for
making modifications to it.  For a library, complete source code means
all the source code for all modules it contains, plus any associated
interface definition files, plus the scripts used to control compilation
and installation of the library.
     </para>
     <para>
Activities other than copying, distribution and modification are not
covered by this License; they are outside its scope.  The act of
running a program using the Library is not restricted, and output from
such a program is covered only if its contents constitute a work based
on the Library (independent of the use of the Library in a tool for
writing it).  Whether that is true depends on what the Library does
and what the program that uses the Library does.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
You may copy and distribute verbatim copies of the Library's
complete source code as you receive it, in any medium, provided that
you conspicuously and appropriately publish on each copy an
appropriate copyright notice and disclaimer of warranty; keep intact
all the notices that refer to this License and to the absence of any
warranty; and distribute a copy of this License along with the
Library.
     </para>
     <para>
You may charge a fee for the physical act of transferring a copy,
and you may at your option offer warranty protection in exchange for a
fee.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
You may modify your copy or copies of the Library or any portion
of it, thus forming a work based on the Library, and copy and
distribute such modifications or work under the terms of Section 1
above, provided that you also meet all of these conditions:
     </para>
     <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
       <para>
The modified work must itself be a software library.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
You must cause the files modified to carry prominent notices
stating that you changed the files and the date of any change.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
You must cause the whole of the work to be licensed at no
charge to all third parties under the terms of this License.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
If a facility in the modified Library refers to a function or a
table of data to be supplied by an application program that uses
the facility, other than as an argument passed when the facility
is invoked, then you must make a good faith effort to ensure that,
in the event an application does not supply such function or
table, the facility still operates, and performs whatever part of
its purpose remains meaningful.
       </para>
       <para>
(For example, a function in a library to compute square roots has
a purpose that is entirely well-defined independent of the
application.  Therefore, Subsection 2d requires that any
application-supplied function or table used by this function must
be optional: if the application does not supply it, the square
root function must still compute square roots.)
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
     <para>
These requirements apply to the modified work as a whole.  If
identifiable sections of that work are not derived from the Library,
and can be reasonably considered independent and separate works in
themselves, then this License, and its terms, do not apply to those
sections when you distribute them as separate works.  But when you
distribute the same sections as part of a whole which is a work based
on the Library, the distribution of the whole must be on the terms of
this License, whose permissions for other licensees extend to the
entire whole, and thus to each and every part regardless of who wrote
it.
     </para>
     <para>
Thus, it is not the intent of this section to claim rights or contest
your rights to work written entirely by you; rather, the intent is to
exercise the right to control the distribution of derivative or
collective works based on the Library.
     </para>
     <para>
In addition, mere aggregation of another work not based on the Library
with the Library (or with a work based on the Library) on a volume of
a storage or distribution medium does not bring the other work under
the scope of this License.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
You may opt to apply the terms of the ordinary GNU General Public
License instead of this License to a given copy of the Library.  To do
this, you must alter all the notices that refer to this License, so
that they refer to the ordinary GNU General Public License, version 2,
instead of to this License.  (If a newer version than version 2 of the
ordinary GNU General Public License has appeared, then you can specify
that version instead if you wish.)  Do not make any other change in
these notices.
     </para>
     <para>
Once this change is made in a given copy, it is irreversible for
that copy, so the ordinary GNU General Public License applies to all
subsequent copies and derivative works made from that copy.
     </para>
     <para>
This option is useful when you wish to copy part of the code of
the Library into a program that is not a library.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
You may copy and distribute the Library (or a portion or
derivative of it, under Section 2) in object code or executable form
under the terms of Sections 1 and 2 above provided that you accompany
it with the complete corresponding machine-readable source code, which
must be distributed under the terms of Sections 1 and 2 above on a
medium customarily used for software interchange.
     </para>
     <para>
If distribution of object code is made by offering access to copy
from a designated place, then offering equivalent access to copy the
source code from the same place satisfies the requirement to
distribute the source code, even though third parties are not
compelled to copy the source along with the object code.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
A program that contains no derivative of any portion of the
Library, but is designed to work with the Library by being compiled or
linked with it, is called a "work that uses the Library".  Such a
work, in isolation, is not a derivative work of the Library, and
therefore falls outside the scope of this License.
     </para>
     <para>
However, linking a "work that uses the Library" with the Library
creates an executable that is a derivative of the Library (because it
contains portions of the Library), rather than a "work that uses the
library".  The executable is therefore covered by this License.
Section 6 states terms for distribution of such executables.
     </para>
     <para>
When a "work that uses the Library" uses material from a header file
that is part of the Library, the object code for the work may be a
derivative work of the Library even though the source code is not.
Whether this is true is especially significant if the work can be
linked without the Library, or if the work is itself a library.  The
threshold for this to be true is not precisely defined by law.
     </para>
     <para>
If such an object file uses only numerical parameters, data
structure layouts and accessors, and small macros and small inline
functions (ten lines or less in length), then the use of the object
file is unrestricted, regardless of whether it is legally a derivative
work.  (Executables containing this object code plus portions of the
Library will still fall under Section 6.)
     </para>
     <para>
Otherwise, if the work is a derivative of the Library, you may
distribute the object code for the work under the terms of Section 6.
Any executables containing that work also fall under Section 6,
whether or not they are linked directly with the Library itself.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
As an exception to the Sections above, you may also combine or
link a "work that uses the Library" with the Library to produce a
work containing portions of the Library, and distribute that work
under terms of your choice, provided that the terms permit
modification of the work for the customer's own use and reverse
engineering for debugging such modifications.
     </para>
     <para>
You must give prominent notice with each copy of the work that the
Library is used in it and that the Library and its use are covered by
this License.  You must supply a copy of this License.  If the work
during execution displays copyright notices, you must include the
copyright notice for the Library among them, as well as a reference
directing the user to the copy of this License.  Also, you must do one
of these things:
     </para>
     <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
       <para>
Accompany the work with the complete corresponding
machine-readable source code for the Library including whatever
changes were used in the work (which must be distributed under
Sections 1 and 2 above); and, if the work is an executable linked
with the Library, with the complete machine-readable "work that
uses the Library", as object code and/or source code, so that the
user can modify the Library and then relink to produce a modified
executable containing the modified Library.  (It is understood
that the user who changes the contents of definitions files in the
Library will not necessarily be able to recompile the application
to use the modified definitions.)
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
Use a suitable shared library mechanism for linking with the Library.  A
suitable mechanism is one that (1) uses at run time a copy of the
library already present on the user's computer system, rather than
copying library functions into the executable, and (2) will operate
properly with a modified version of the library, if the user installs
one, as long as the modified version is interface-compatible with the
version that the work was made with.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
Accompany the work with a written offer, valid for at
least three years, to give the same user the materials
specified in Subsection 6a, above, for a charge no more
than the cost of performing this distribution.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
If distribution of the work is made by offering access to copy
from a designated place, offer equivalent access to copy the above
specified materials from the same place.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
Verify that the user has already received a copy of these
materials or that you have already sent this user a copy.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
     <para>
For an executable, the required form of the "work that uses the
Library" must include any data and utility programs needed for
reproducing the executable from it.  However, as a special exception,
the materials to be distributed need not include anything that is
normally distributed (in either source or binary form) with the major
components (compiler, kernel, and so on) of the operating system on
which the executable runs, unless that component itself accompanies the
executable.
     </para>
     <para>
It may happen that this requirement contradicts the license
restrictions of other proprietary libraries that do not normally
accompany the operating system.  Such a contradiction means you cannot
use both them and the Library together in an executable that you
distribute.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
You may place library facilities that are a work based on the
Library side-by-side in a single library together with other library
facilities not covered by this License, and distribute such a combined
library, provided that the separate distribution of the work based on
the Library and of the other library facilities is otherwise
permitted, and provided that you do these two things:
     </para>
     <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
      <listitem>
       <para>
Accompany the combined library with a copy of the same work
based on the Library, uncombined with any other library
facilities.  This must be distributed under the terms of the
Sections above.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
Give prominent notice with the combined library of the fact
that part of it is a work based on the Library, and explaining
where to find the accompanying uncombined form of the same work.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
You may not copy, modify, sublicense, link with, or distribute
the Library except as expressly provided under this License.  Any
attempt otherwise to copy, modify, sublicense, link with, or
distribute the Library is void, and will automatically terminate your
rights under this License.  However, parties who have received copies,
or rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
terminated so long as such parties remain in full compliance.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
You are not required to accept this License, since you have not
signed it.  However, nothing else grants you permission to modify or
distribute the Library or its derivative works.  These actions are
prohibited by law if you do not accept this License.  Therefore, by
modifying or distributing the Library (or any work based on the
Library), you indicate your acceptance of this License to do so, and
all its terms and conditions for copying, distributing or modifying
the Library or works based on it.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
Each time you redistribute the Library (or any work based on the
Library), the recipient automatically receives a license from the
original licensor to copy, distribute, link with or modify the Library
subject to these terms and conditions.  You may not impose any further
restrictions on the recipients' exercise of the rights granted herein.
You are not responsible for enforcing compliance by third parties with
this License.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
If, as a consequence of a court judgment or allegation of patent
infringement or for any other reason (not limited to patent issues),
conditions are imposed on you (whether by court order, agreement or
otherwise) that contradict the conditions of this License, they do not
excuse you from the conditions of this License.  If you cannot
distribute so as to satisfy simultaneously your obligations under this
License and any other pertinent obligations, then as a consequence you
may not distribute the Library at all.  For example, if a patent
license would not permit royalty-free redistribution of the Library by
all those who receive copies directly or indirectly through you, then
the only way you could satisfy both it and this License would be to
refrain entirely from distribution of the Library.
     </para>
     <para>
If any portion of this section is held invalid or unenforceable under any
particular circumstance, the balance of the section is intended to apply,
and the section as a whole is intended to apply in other circumstances.
     </para>
     <para>
It is not the purpose of this section to induce you to infringe any
patents or other property right claims or to contest validity of any
such claims; this section has the sole purpose of protecting the
integrity of the free software distribution system which is
implemented by public license practices.  Many people have made
generous contributions to the wide range of software distributed
through that system in reliance on consistent application of that
system; it is up to the author/donor to decide if he or she is willing
to distribute software through any other system and a licensee cannot
impose that choice.
     </para>
     <para>
This section is intended to make thoroughly clear what is believed to
be a consequence of the rest of this License.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
If the distribution and/or use of the Library is restricted in
certain countries either by patents or by copyrighted interfaces, the
original copyright holder who places the Library under this License may add
an explicit geographical distribution limitation excluding those countries,
so that distribution is permitted only in or among countries not thus
excluded.  In such case, this License incorporates the limitation as if
written in the body of this License.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
The Free Software Foundation may publish revised and/or new
versions of the Lesser General Public License from time to time.
Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present version,
but may differ in detail to address new problems or concerns.
     </para>
     <para>
Each version is given a distinguishing version number.  If the Library
specifies a version number of this License which applies to it and
"any later version", you have the option of following the terms and
conditions either of that version or of any later version published by
the Free Software Foundation.  If the Library does not specify a
license version number, you may choose any version ever published by
the Free Software Foundation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
If you wish to incorporate parts of the Library into other free
programs whose distribution conditions are incompatible with these,
write to the author to ask for permission.  For software which is
copyrighted by the Free Software Foundation, write to the Free
Software Foundation; we sometimes make exceptions for this.  Our
decision will be guided by the two goals of preserving the free status
of all derivatives of our free software and of promoting the sharing
and reuse of software generally.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
BECAUSE THE LIBRARY IS LICENSED FREE OF CHARGE, THERE IS NO
WARRANTY FOR THE LIBRARY, TO THE EXTENT PERMITTED BY APPLICABLE LAW.
EXCEPT WHEN OTHERWISE STATED IN WRITING THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND/OR
OTHER PARTIES PROVIDE THE LIBRARY "AS IS" WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY
KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
PURPOSE.  THE ENTIRE RISK AS TO THE QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THE
LIBRARY IS WITH YOU.  SHOULD THE LIBRARY PROVE DEFECTIVE, YOU ASSUME
THE COST OF ALL NECESSARY SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
IN NO EVENT UNLESS REQUIRED BY APPLICABLE LAW OR AGREED TO IN
WRITING WILL ANY COPYRIGHT HOLDER, OR ANY OTHER PARTY WHO MAY MODIFY
AND/OR REDISTRIBUTE THE LIBRARY AS PERMITTED ABOVE, BE LIABLE TO YOU
FOR DAMAGES, INCLUDING ANY GENERAL, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL OR
CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES ARISING OUT OF THE USE OR INABILITY TO USE THE
LIBRARY (INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO LOSS OF DATA OR DATA BEING
RENDERED INACCURATE OR LOSSES SUSTAINED BY YOU OR THIRD PARTIES OR A
FAILURE OF THE LIBRARY TO OPERATE WITH ANY OTHER SOFTWARE), EVEN IF
SUCH HOLDER OR OTHER PARTY HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH
DAMAGES.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
   <bridgehead renderas="sect3">How to Apply These Terms to Your New Libraries</bridgehead>
   <para>
If you develop a new library, and you want it to be of the greatest
possible use to the public, we recommend making it free software that
everyone can redistribute and change.  You can do so by permitting
redistribution under these terms (or, alternatively, under the terms of the
ordinary General Public License).
   </para>
   <para>
To apply these terms, attach the following notices to the library.  It is
safest to attach them to the start of each source file to most effectively
convey the exclusion of warranty; and each file should have at least the
"copyright" line and a pointer to where the full notice is found.
   </para>
   <screen><replaceable>one line to give the library's name and an idea of what it does.</replaceable>
Copyright (C) <replaceable>year</replaceable>  <replaceable>name of author</replaceable>

This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of the License, or (at
your option) any later version.

This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
Lesser General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307,
USA.
</screen>
   <para>
Also add information on how to contact you by electronic and paper mail.
   </para>
   <para>
You should also get your employer (if you work as a programmer) or your
school, if any, to sign a "copyright disclaimer" for the library, if
necessary.  Here is a sample; alter the names:
   </para>
   <screen>Yoyodyne, Inc., hereby disclaims all copyright interest in the library
`Frob' (a library for tweaking knobs) written by James Random Hacker.

<varname>signature of Ty Coon</varname>, 1 April 1990
Ty Coon, President of Vice
</screen>
   <para>
That's all there is to it!
   </para>
</appendix>

 <appendix xml:id="glibc-Documentation-License">
  <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
  <titleabbrev>DEĞİŞTİRİLEMEZ BÖLÜM. (ingilizce)</titleabbrev>
  <para/>
  <xi:include href="gfdl.xml" xpointer="gfdl-inner"/>
 </appendix>

 <index xml:id="glibc-cp" condition="multi-index" label="i">
  <title>Kavramlar Dizini</title>
  <titleabbrev>Kavramlar ve terimler dizini</titleabbrev>
 </index>

 <index xml:id="glibc-tp" condition="multi-index" label="ii">
  <title>Veri Türleri Dizini</title>
  <titleabbrev>Veri türleri ve tür niteleyiciler dizini</titleabbrev>
 </index>

 <index xml:id="glibc-fn" condition="multi-index" label="iii">
  <title>İşlevler Dizini</title>
  <titleabbrev>İşlevler ve işlev benzeri makrolar dizini</titleabbrev>
 </index>
 <index xml:id="glibc-vr" condition="multi-index" label="iv">
  <title>Değişkenler Dizini</title>
  <titleabbrev>Değişkenler ve sabit makroları dizini</titleabbrev>
 </index>

 <index xml:id="glibc-pg" condition="multi-index" label="v">
  <title>Dosyalar Dizini</title>
  <titleabbrev>Yazılımlar ve dosyalar dizini</titleabbrev>
 </index>
</book>
