<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ********************************************************************
       man8/nologin.8.xml, Shadow-utils 4.11.1, BSD3, NBB - Ekim 2022
     ******************************************************************** -->
<refentry xml:id="man8-nologin" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="tr">
 <info>
  <keywordset>
   <keyword>Linux, manpage, kütüphane, kitaplık, belge, belgeler</keyword>
   <keyword>kabuk, komut, kullanıcı, yardım, kılavuz, Shadow-utils</keyword>
   <keyword>nologin, kişisel, kabuk, login.defs, grup, sistem</keyword>
   <keyword>parola, kimlik, ekle, politika, chroot, prefix, root</keyword>
  </keywordset>
 </info>
 <refmeta>
  <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
  <refentrytitle>nologin</refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo>
   <sectdesc>Sistem Yönetim Komutları</sectdesc>
   <source>Shadow-utils 4.11.1</source>
   <date>Şubat 2022</date>
  </refmiscinfo>
  <legalnotice>
   <title>Yasal Uyarı</title>
   <screen> * Özgün Belgenin Lisans ve Telif Hakkı bilgileri:
 *
 * Copyright 2004, FreeBSD Project
 * All rights reserved.
 *
 * Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without
 * modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions
 * are met:
 * 1. Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright
 *    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
 * 2. Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright
 *    notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the
 *    documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
 *
 * THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHOR "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR
 * IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES
 * OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.
 * IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT,
 * INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT
 * NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE,
 * DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY
 * THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
 * (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF
 * THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
</screen>
  </legalnotice>
 </refmeta>
 <refnamediv>
  <refname>nologin</refname>
  <refpurpose>oturum açılmasını nezaketle reddeder</refpurpose>
 </refnamediv>
 <refsynopsisdiv>
  <cmdsynopsis>
   <command>nologin</command>
  </cmdsynopsis>
 </refsynopsisdiv>
 <refsect1><title>AÇIKLAMA</title>
  <para>
   <command>nologin</command> komutu, hesabın mevcut olmadığını belirten bir ileti gösterir ve sıfırdan farklı bir değerle çıkar. Devre dışı bırakılmış hesaplar için yedek bir kabuk alanı olarak tasarlanmıştır.
  </para>
  <para>
   Tüm hesapların oturum açmasının engellenmesi konusu <uri xl:href="man5-nologin"/> sayfasında incelenebilir.
  </para>
  <para>
   <code>SSH_ORIGINAL_COMMAND</code> doldurulursa, günlüğe kaydedilir.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
 <refsect1><title>İLGİLİ BELGELER</title>
  <para>
   <uri xl:href="man1-login"/>, <uri xl:href="man5-nologin"/>
  </para>
 </refsect1>
 <refsect1><title>TARİHÇE</title>
  <para>
   <command>nologin</command> komutu BSD 4.4’te kullanılmaya başladı.
  </para>
 </refsect1>
 <refsect1><title>ÇEVİREN</title>
  <simpara>© 2022 Nilgün Belma Bugüner</simpara>
  &manpages.notice;
 </refsect1>
</refentry>
